Guide to the Tamar Carroll Oral Histories on Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) OH.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Shaw, Susan, July 26, 2004; cuid34420
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll in Northampton, MA on July 26, 2004. The interview covers Susan Shaw's involvement in Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) and the women's health issues that were of interest to her during her involvement in WHAM!. Shaw describes the way in which she became interested in activism, beginning in high school during Ronald Reagan's presidency and her focus on the United States' involvement in Central America and the movement to end apartheid in South Africa. She describes her introduction to WHAM! in 1991 or 1992, after she finished college and moved to New York City. She relates the excitement she felt at the way WHAM! was focusing on different issues of women's health, particularly because she was not interested in the clinic defense movement and was glad to have other topics to focus on, in particular sterilization abuses, women with AIDS, and health issues faced by women of color. She discusses the fact that WHAM! was mainly white, college-educated people, many of whom were lesbians, that they wanted to form coalitions with groups that reflected them but Shaw wanted to broaden the coalitions to groups of different races and classes. She also discusses her work on the New Member Packet for WHAM!, in the interest of making the organization easier for people to join and understand. Other topics include Shaw's work at the People with AIDS Coalition and the skills she learned at WHAM! and how she still used them in her work at the time of the interview.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_3)
  - Preservation Copy (Box 1, Cd OH-66-007-01)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-007-01)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_066_ER_20
- WHAM! Group Interview, December 16, 2005; cuid34425
  Charles K. Alexander II is labor leader, socialist, feminist, and women's rights activist. He is a former member of Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), Freedom Socialist Party, Radical Women, Reproductive Rights Coalition. In the 1980s, he was a shop steward in an unspecified labor union at New York University.
  Mark Jacquinot is a lawyer and former member of WHAM!. Jacquinot lived in Iowa in the 1970s and was a founder and secretary-treasurer of Crisis in Iowa, a member of the Ames Pro-Choice Coalition, before moving to Buffalo, NY in 1984 to attend law school and moving to New York City in 1988.
  Mary Anne Staniszewski is an art and cultural historian, and former member of WHAM! and the Reproductive Rights Coalition. She was a member of the media wing of WHAM!.
  This interview was conducted by Tamar Carroll at an unspecified location on December 16, 2005. The interview was recorded on video. Charles K. Alexander II, Mark Jacquinot, and Mary Anne Staniszewski discuss their backgrounds, what drew them to Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!), and their experiences in WHAM!. All three were involved in the Reproductive Rights Coalition (RRC) and were members of WHAM! from its beginning. Alexander and Staniszewski describe the beginnings of WHAM! as the direct action committee of RRC and how it eventually separated to become its own organization. They discuss the differences between the two organizations and their preference for WHAM! and its philosophy. Jacquinot and Alexander discuss their work in abortion clinic defense and protests in New York City in the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_5)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-012)
- WHAM! Reunion, October 15, 2005; cuid34426
  Historical Note
  The Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) Reunion took place at the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives on October 15, 2005. The event included presentations by a panel of former WHAM! members and Tamar Carroll, followed by comments and questions from former WHAM! members in the audience. The panel included Mary Anne Staniszewski, Michele Tepper, Marian Cole, Leslie Wolf, Meryl Levin, and Carroll.
  The Women's Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM!) Reunion was recorded on video on October 15, 2005. The event is opened by former head of Tamiment Michael H. Nash who discusses the relationship between Tamiment and WHAM!, Carroll's dissertation project, and the work of the Tamiment Library. Levin shares a slideshow of images from WHAM! events and direct actions. Carroll discusses her dissertation topic and her relationship with the former members of WHAM! with whom she conducted oral histories. The bulk of the reunion focuses on the presentations of Staniszewski, Tepper, Cole, Wolf, and Levin who each discuss how they became active in WHAM! and the importance of WHAM!'s work. They focus on what made WHAM! special; the coalitions WHAM! formed with other activist groups, especially ACT-UP and the Reproductive Rights Coalition; and the ways in which WHAM! impacted each of them individually. The remainder of the recording includes people from the audience sharing their experiences with WHAM!.
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cd TW_OH_066_6)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 091, Cd OH-66-013)
- WHAM! Action, 1990; cuid34427 (Box 1, Audiocassette OH.066.015)